the baby book
published by the prudential insurance
company of america
sometime between 1912
and 1922.
the baby
useful information as to its care
feeding and training
the mother-to-be
unusual demands will be made upon the
strength and health of the woman who is
about to become a mother
and unusual steps should be taken by the
prospective parent to conserve both
she must remember that she has her
baby's life as well as her own in her
keeping
and this should prompt her to be doubly
careful
she should anticipate the coming event
in a happy cheerful spirit and should
not be at all anxious about it
rather she should be natural that is all
the little one will be one of very many
born daily without dangerous results to
their mothers don't worry
the rules of health are few and simple
and for the most part the same is for
other times except that it is necessary
to observe them with much thoughtfulness
fresh air is a main essential and if
this the mother-to-be should get as much
as she can
for it is fresh air that makes good
blood and with sunshine it is nature's
best tonic
exercise and good air should go together
and to secure these a short walk should
be taken during the afternoon and
evening when the weather will permit
the air in the rooms should be fresh and
free of impurities at all times
especially at night when the sleeping
room windows should be well opened
plenty of rest and sleep are necessary
one should retire early
and if possible take a short nap during
the afternoon
don't forget that sleep is nature's
great restorer
it refreshes the mind and the body
and gives new strength to both
the food should be simple and easy to
digest
it should be kept pure and free from all
germs
impure food means trouble
meat is never a necessity
some physicians advise against its use
during the last few months but it can be
eaten in small quantities if one likes
it
cereals and milk may be eaten freely
so may nearly all ripe fruit and
vegetables but they must be well washed
to remove any germs which they carry
highly seasoned foods and alcoholic
beverages should not be used
weak
tea and coffee and plenty of pure milk
may be taken
several glasses of water every day help
to drain the impurities from the body
there should be a healthy movement of
the bowels every day or trouble will
follow and possibly disease
a glass or two of hot water taken before
breakfast will help in this direction
the pores of the skin should be kept
open by bathing frequently
if a tub bath cannot be taken a sponge
bath is a fairly good substitute while a
hot water sits bath taken at night is of
great value
the breasts should be carefully looked
after
they should be washed each day with cold
water and soap and a little vaseline
rubbed into them as well as on the
nipples
take good care of the teeth by brushing
them frequently
the head should be well washed once a
month and the hair carefully brushed
every night
if the hair is dry rub a little vaseline
into the scalp two or three times each
week
the mother should have the best of care
at this time and be attended by a good
doctor if she cannot afford it she
should not hesitate to go to a hospital
and ask for the help and advice gladly
furnished her there
the doctor will tell you what to have
ready for the time when the baby comes
don't wait until the last day but have
everything prepared one or two months
before they are needed
follow the doctor's advice carefully in
all things
when the baby has come
like a little pink bunch of folded human
rose leaves the baby has come into a new
strange and cold world
as soon as the baby's eyes nose and
mouth
should be washed with barack bracic acid
solution the eyes particularly to
prevent possible blindness
be careful in handling the baby that its
breathing is not interfered with be sure
that it breathes freely
do not lay it face downward
it should be well rubbed with olive oil
and then allowed a good rest
warmth is what the tiny arrival now
needs
it should be wrapped well in clean warm
coverings to keep it from being chilled
its feet and hands will tell you when it
is warm
if it is not sufficiently nurtured in
this regard colic is very likely to
develop
the baby sleeps better also while warm
and sleep is one of the main needs for
several months
and sleep comes easier to the little one
if it is not disturbed
it should for that reason be left alone
as much as possible
do not have the baby in bed with its
mother
if nothing else is handy a clothes
basket makes a good bed
nursing the baby should be put to the
breast on the first day
the mother should nurse her baby if it
is all possible
as breastfeeding is much safer than the
bottle
the baby that can be breastfed has 10
times the chance it would have if bottle
fed
90 to 95 percent of mothers can nurse
their babies if they are willing to take
the time and means to do so
the baby does not need any milk for the
first three days but it should be put to
the breast every four or five hours
during this period
if the mother drinks milk freely before
confinement she will probably be able to
nurse her child
the nipples and the child's mouth should
be well washed before each feeding
don't give to the newly born baby sugar
butter
honey or anything but a teaspoonful of
warm water which has been boiled
this with the watery secretion from the
mother's breast which comes before the
milk giving period
will put the baby's bowels in order and
prepare its stomach for the heavier diet
later on
on the third day and for a month
afterward the child should be put to the
breast every two hours during the day
and once or twice during the night
about 10 times in 24 hours
regular feeding times should be insisted
upon
during all of this time the baby should
be gaining weight from four to eight
ounces a week
it should be weighed regularly to see if
it is growing properly
if the gain is much less than this or
there is a loss of weight consult a
physician
it is very important that the mother who
is nursing a child should have good
health
nervous shocks or frights may change the
quantity and kind of the milk
plenty of good nourishing food and cow's
milk should be taken as well as rest
exercise and sleep
drugs and alcoholic liquors should not
be used unless ordered by the doctor
some mothers have not enough milk of the
right value to nourish the baby or they
may have none at all
if the former the mixed feeding plan may
be followed
the mother's milk being used so far as
it will go
after which other kinds should also be
given
cow's milk is the best but it is so much
stronger than mother's milk that before
giving it to babies it should be mixed
with boiled water
first cooled or barley water
three parts of water to one milk
later adding a little fresh cream and
sugar
or sugar of milk
however it is safest always to have a
doctor advice fully as to the way in
which the child should be bottle-fed
care of the infant
the baby's clothing should be soft light
and warm
it may be plain and not expensive
woolen garments give the most pleasant
warmth and should be used
a flannel band should be worn over the
stomach for a few months
two of them will be enough for a day in
a night change
over the band should come a long-sleeved
wool shirt
then a petticoat of flannel
extending below the feet
and overall a dress of soft material
always remember the child must be kept
warm but the clothes should not bind in
any way
it is much better to have loose
coverings which allow for a warm layer
of air next to the body
the weight of the clothing should vary
with the weather and the seasons
the wrong kind and not enough often
cause a cold bronchitis pneumonia or
bowel trouble
a good supply of napkins or diapers
should be on hand
cleanliness aids perfect health so the
mother need hardly be warned with regard
to the use of these articles
always keep the napkins on the baby warm
and dry and see to it that the soiled
napkins are washed and cleaned with much
care
never put a damp napkin on a baby you
wish to keep strong and good tempered
the baby's mouth should be washed out
daily with absorbent cotton wound around
the mother's little finger and soaked in
warm water or boraxic acid solution
one teaspoon full of boraxic acid to a
tumbler of water
this may prevent what is called thrush
or sprue from appearing on the lips and
inside the mouth of the child
the baby should have a bath in
well-heated water every morning
for the first couple of weeks it may be
bathed on the lap of the mother and
after that in the tub
wash its head carefully with soap and
warm water not using much soap if the
skin chafes or is tender
if brown spots appear on its head rub
olive oil on the scalp
talcum powder should be shaken into the
folds of the skin
under the arms and between the legs
always be sure the air in the room where
the baby sleeps is fresh
the room should be well aired at all
times
much care however being taken to sea
that the baby is properly covered and in
no draft
be as anxious for the air as you would
be careful of your child
perhaps no better rule could be laid
down
after the baby is a week old if properly
clothed and protected from the rays of
the sun or cold breezes it may be left
outdoors in clear weather during the
middle of the day
the baby cannot have too much sleep
see that it gets enough
its brain tires easily and sleep
overcomes this
no fixed rule can be outlined in this
connection but a normal baby during the
first three months
should sleep nearly all the time and
during the following three months
perhaps three quarters of the time
its period of required sleep will
gradually lessen after that
let it sleep all it wants to
in later months it may be possible to
regulate the hours of sleep for the baby
firmness and training when the time
comes will mean much to the mother's
comfort
feeding the baby how much
and how often whether it is breastfed or
bottle-fed is shown by the table below
also how much the baby should weigh
there is a table here
of feedings
that i will copy and add into the text
section
of the description section of this video
as with sleep the mother will soon find
the baby becomes a creature of habit and
can be taught to feed it about the same
hours each day
don't feed too often nor feed too much
and let the baby sleep after feeding and
whenever else it wants to
growth and development
the baby should gain rapidly in weight
in size
in five months it should double and in
12 months triple its first weight as
shown by the foregoing table
there is usually an average gain in
height of one inch a month for the first
four months
and a gain of half an inch a month for
the next eight months
or a total gain of eight inches for the
first year
after that the weight should increase
for several years at the rate of about
five pounds a year and its height
increase for a couple of years at the
rate of four inches a year
during the fourth and fifth years
three inches a year after that
two inches a year until the tenth year
has passed while these figures are
general any considerable variation from
them suggests that something is wrong
the baby's first tooth appears about the
seventh month
the two central lower teeth generally
coming first
from the eighth to the twelfth month the
four upper central teeth usually appear
thus making six teeth at the end of the
first year
within the next six months there should
be 12 teeth including the two lower
central and the four double front teeth
in two years there should be four more
the two eye and the two stomach teeth
while in two and one half years the
child's entire set should be complete
including the four back double teeth
this is the general course but there are
cases in which the teeth do not come in
in the order given
teething is a natural process and need
not be attended by much pain or distress
there may be some loss of
sleep or appetite some fever or vomiting
lasting for two or three days but if the
symptoms are worse than this there is
reason to fear that the trouble is not
teething but improper food and care
when in doubt consult a doctor
the baby should hold up its head when it
is four months old by the seventh or
eighth month be able to sit erect
and may make an attempt to walk during
the ninth or tenth month although it
should not be encouraged to do so until
the twelfth month as its bones and
muscles are too soft
by the 15th month it should be able to
run about the room
when the baby is sick
nothing in this book or any other book
will take the place of the doctor when
the baby is really sick
still it is well to know the signs of a
few important diseases and know what to
do in their early stages or until the
doctor arrives
the mother's good judgment is best at
these times
she should keep a watchful eye upon
everything that may affect the baby's
health
a very simple thing
may start the trouble
the child's clothing may be too warm or
the band over the stomach too tight
the watchful mother will be quick to
find the source of the trouble
and by doing a few simple things can
often save sending for the doctor
indigestion
it is the bottle-fed baby that usually
has trouble with its stomach
breastfed children rarely have trouble
if the mother uses care in what she eats
and drinks herself and how she lives
generally
but the baby whether breastfed or bottle
fed
may be fed too often
too much or too rapidly
there will be restlessness and vomiting
while the matter discharged from the
bowels may be of a greenish color
in such cases a teaspoon full of castor
oil should be given at once
and all food stopped for a time so that
the stomach may have a rest
in starting the feeding again less food
should be given at first and in the case
of bottle-fed babies some barley water
should be mixed with the food
colic is very common in young babies and
its symptoms are seldom mistaken
the baby twists face suddenly as if in
pain
draws up its feet and clenches its hands
its stomach is hard and swollen with gas
the remedy is to give an injection of
hot water or give castor oil
placing the baby in a warm bath will
usually relieve the pain
it is not wise to feed the baby so often
if it has colic as its powers of
digestion are generally weak
constipation
is not likely to occur if the child is
taught early to have its bowels move
regularly
a small amount of olive oil about a
teaspoonful may be given from time to
time if the constipation becomes a habit
for immediate relief a small quantity of
warm soap suds sweet oil or a little
glycerin may be injected into the bowels
convulsions are always a sign of serious
trouble and should be treated by a
doctor if possible
if no doctor can be had the best thing
to do is put the baby in a warm mustard
bath for 5 or 10 minutes or wrap around
a towel soaked with warm water in which
is placed a little mustard then wrap it
up in a warm blanket for about 10
minutes
at the same time a cold wet towel should
be applied to its head
as convulsive fits often come from
stomach and bowel trouble
an injection should be given as in the
case of
colic when the attack is over the baby
should be kept very quiet for a time as
it is nervous
any excitement may bring on another fit
spitting up of milk is generally due to
overfeeding or it may be caused
sometimes by the child's stomach band
being too tight
make sure that the latter is not the
case before looking elsewhere for the
cause
if overfeeding be the cause
cut down the number of feedings and if
the child is bottle-fed
dilute the food with cold boiled water
if breastfed remove the child from the
breast occasionally
it may also be necessary for the mother
to reduce her own diet
whooping cough is a dangerous disease
and is very common in young children
it is contagious while it lasts so that
the child who has it should be kept away
from other children
it begins like a cold but the cough
instead of getting better gets worse
especially at night the child becoming
bred in the face
breathless and exhausted
the disease may last from three to four
months
it can be helped a good deal by seeing
that the child has plenty of fresh air
day and night and that is protected from
drafts
measles is the most contagious of all
diseases to which children are liable
and the most common
it is so common that many mothers look
upon it as certain sooner or later and
expose their children to it deliberately
believing that if they get it when
they're older
they will have it worse
this however is a mistake
it is never wise or good policy to
expose a child to unnecessary risk and
measles are risky and often fatal when
the child is not carefully nursed
the disease begins with a running from
the nose
feverishness and the usual symptoms of a
bad cold
followed at the end of three days by a
red rash on the skin
the spots being about the size of peas
the red spots disappear after a few days
the child usually recovering in about
nine days
the important point in nursing measles
is to keep the child warm in bed and to
guard against taking cold
thrush or sprue
is a common ailment in very young
children especially among those that are
bottle-fed
it is known by small white patches
breaking out inside the mouth about the
gums
on the tongue etc
and arises generally from want of
cleanliness in feeding the child
the mouth may be washed every three
hours with borax and glycerin
one cannot be too careful in keeping the
bottle and nipple clean and seeing that
the milk supplied is clean and pure
eczema is a disease very common in small
babies
the skin becomes irritable and itchy and
is of a bright red color and full of
little scales
any part of the baby's skin may be
affected in this way but the cheeks
forehead and scalp are the parts
commonly affected
eczema may come from many causes
principally indigestion
anything with which irritates the skin
such as strong soap discharge from the
nose or ear or a soiled napkin may cause
eczema
whatever the cause it must be sought for
and removed before a cure can be
affected
the food supply should be reduced or
weakened if necessary and the condition
of the bowels particularly attended to
where the itching is severe the baby's
hands should be tied up in mittens to
prevent worse trouble from scratching
itself
ricketts is a constitutional disease
which comes from poor nourishment
the child either has not had good food
or is unable to digest the food it has
had
hence it is weak irritable and backward
in growth
it is small for its age
also light and is late in teething
if it is suspected that the child has
this disease lose no time in seeking the
advice of a physician
adenoids are certain abnormal overgrowth
of the flesh at the back of the nose and
throat
they are common in young children and
are often found in connection with
enlarged tonsils
if the overgrowth is only slight it will
not cause much trouble but if it is
large the child will have a running of
the nose
and the usual symptoms of a cold in the
head
it can breathe only through the mouth
and by always keeping the mouth open has
a dull stupid expression
advanced cases should be treated by a
doctor
physical and moral training
training should go hand in hand with
physical training
your baby is born with lots of energy
and it behooves the parents to give the
energy a wise direction
after the third month babies should not
as a rule be nursed during the night
if this habit gets started it will be
difficult to break
the mother should show firmness in this
matter
let the child cry
a little rather than that you should be
in attendance upon it day and night
the crying will do it good anyhow and so
will a little self-denial
do not handle the baby too often or
train it to expect too much attention
from the family
never give the child a pacifier or
comforter to keep it quiet
it is not what its name denotes
it is a distributor of serious
contagious diseases consumption
diphtheria and even worse
apart from the danger the habit of
sucking at a rubber nipple produces
swollen lips
puts the teeth and mouth out of shape
and brings on the troublesome disease
called adenoids
the same is true of the habit of sucking
the thumb or fingers
all such excessive exercise of the mouth
and lips leads to an undue and unsightly
development of the parts concerned
the parents must enforce such rules as
are known to be good for the child
it may not take its food
it may have to grade a liking for one
kind of food and a dislike for another
such obstinacy should not be tolerated
when the child is thus unruly it should
be punished by being deprived of
something it likes
until it finally gives in after which it
sweeps or its toys may be restored to it
undressing it and putting it to bed or
compelling it to go hungry for a while
will generally correct any unreasonable
food fancies the child may have
the baby that is breastfed will not give
up its special privilege without a
struggle
nevertheless it should be made to give
it up or at least a commencement should
be made in this direction
about the sixth or seventh month
after that
time there is generally a falling off in
the quality of the mother's milk
the process of weaning should be carried
out gradually
bottle feedings being given in place of
breastfeeding first once a day
a few days later
twice a day
and so on until the bottle feeding
entirely replaces the breastfeeding
a few useful hints
if a child is feverish omit solid foods
put to bed and call a doctor
babies often suffer from thirst and have
no manner of expressing their desire
except to cry which is often thought to
mean hunger instead of thirst
even a nursing baby needs pure water
occasionally
if a child frets and wants something out
of regular feeding hours offer a drink
of cool pure water that has been
distilled or boiled
a wakeful baby
will often drop into a quiet and restful
sleep
after a few sips of cool water
not cold
a baby should cry more or less to keep
the lungs well expanded
never let a child or infant sleep in the
room with a sick person
the baby's stomach is intended for food
and drink
avoid therefore giving medicines until
they are actually needed
useful recipes
arrowroot water
take two teaspoonfuls of best arrowroot
and a pint of water
simmer for five minutes stirring
constantly
album in water
the white of one egg half a pint of cold
water
pinch of salt
teaspoonful of brandy
shake well and give a small quantity at
a time
very useful in the case of vomiting
beef juice
take one pound of rare steak cut thick
slightly broil and press out the juice
season with salt and give cold or warmed
barley water
place a teaspoonful of best pearl barley
in a saucepan
add a pint of water and boil for a few
minutes stirring thoroughly all the time
to cleanse the grain
pour the water off the barley replace by
a pint and a half of clean water
simmer gently for an hour and strain
lime water
one teaspoon full of slaked lime
one quart of boiled or distilled water
pour into a bottle and shake three or
four times during the first hour then
allow the lime to settle and pour off
the water
which should be bottled for use
mustard plaster
a good quality of mustard plaster can be
purchased at small cost at any drugstore
to make it home use two parts of mustard
to one of flour
mix with hot water to form a thick paste
and sandwich between strips of cotton
if greater strength is required
lessen the quantity of flour
oatmeal water
a tablespoon of coarsely ground oatmeal
should be placed in a pint of water
simmer gently for an hour
replace the water evaporated